Finding Aid for Michigan Diabetes Research and Training Center Records, 1976-1998
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Michigan Diabetes Research and Training Center records 1976-1998
Michigan Diabetes Research and Training Center Records, 1976-1998
87158 Bimu C500 2
The Michigan Diabetes Research and Training Center group contains administrative files, meeting minutes, and planning documentation related to the establishment and operations of the university's Michigan Diabetes Research and Training Center (MDRTC) from 1976-1998. The MDRTC is one of a nationwide system of diabetes research and training centers designed to support research in diabetes and its management, train researchers and care-givers, and establish model-care units.
4 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Received from the Michigan Diabetes Research and Training Center (Donor no. 7273 ) in 1985, with periodic additions.
The records are open to research.
In 1974, the U.S. Congress passed the Diabetes Mellitus Research and Education Act, thereby establishing the National Diabetes Commission. As part of its mandate to develop a long-term plan for combating diabetes, the Commission recommended establishing a nationwide system of diabetes research and training centers with three prime functions: 1) to support research in diabetes and its management, 2) to train diabetes researchers and care-givers, 3) to establish model patient-care units.
A group of interested faculty members formed a policy committee in May 1976 to examine establishing a center at the University of Michigan. Led by Dr. Stefan S. Fajans, director of the Division of Endocrinology and Metabolism, the group developed a general plan for the proposed Michigan Diabetes Research and Training Center (MDRTC). In October 1976, the National Institute of Arthritis, Metabolism, and Digestive Diseases (NIAMDD, a unit of the National Institutes of Health) officially announced the diabetes research and training centers program and issued grant application guidelines. In September 1977, NIAMDD awarded the University of Michigan a five-year $4.3 million grant from NIAMDD to establish its diabetes research and training center.
At its inception, the MDRTC was organized into "core facilities." The administration core facility oversees the other facilities, which are grouped into three programs: the research development and training program, which oversees six of the core facilities (research and development, biochemistry, biostatistics and data systems, diabetic animal, ligand assay, tissue culture, and human leukocyte antigen); the training and demonstration program, comprised of the diabetes center unit (DCU); and the continuing education and outreach programs, made up of the continuing education and outreach core facility (CEDO) and the educational development and evaluation core facility (EDEV). The administrative backbone of the MDRTC is provided by the Department of Postgraduate Medicine and Health Professions Education and the Department of Internal Medicine's Division of Endocrinology and Metabolism.
The concept behind the MDRTC is to take the knowledge gained by research directly to the patient. The DCU, as the patient care demonstration unit, takes responsibility for linking the lab to the patient. The DCU also serves as a lab for research in professional training and patient care.
The MDRTC uses internal funds each year to support new research, known as "pilot feasibility studies." For advice in its research activities, the MDRTC works with several committees. The Scientific Review Committee is composed of internal and external experts who review applications for pilot feasibility study grants. The Regional Advisory Committee provides feedback from Michigan communities. The University Advisory Committee represents the University of Michigan.
The Michigan Diabetes Research and Training Center records date from 1976 to 1998 and measure 4 linear feet. The Michigan Diabetes Research and Training Center group contains administrative files, meeting minutes, and planning documentation related to the establishment and operations of the university's Michigan Diabetes Research and Training Center (MDRTC) from 1976-1998. The records are arranged into three series, reflecting the center's three main programs: Administrative and Research Development and Training Program, Training and Demonstration Program (Diabetes Center Unit [DCU]), and Continuing Education and Outreach Program.
Subjects:
Diabetes.; University of Michigan. Diabetes Research and Training Center.; University of Michigan. Diabetes Center Unit.; University of Michigan--Research.
- Administrative and Research Development and Training Program
  The Administration and Research Development and Training Program series (1.8 linear feet, 1976-1996) contains records from the administrative core facility and the research development and training program component of the MDRTC; these two components form one series since they are closely intertwined. This series contains the minutes of many committees, including the policy committee (1976), the executive committee (1976-1980), and the scientific review committee (1978-1984). The series documents the planning process behind the MDRTC, the initial grant application and site visit preparation, subsequent grant renewal activities, and the development of research projects.
  - Administrative Core
    - Memos, Research Reports, and Budgets 1979-1984, 5 folders (Box 1)
  - Committees
    - Executive Committee 1976-1980, 3 folders (Box 1)
    - Policy Committee 1976 (Box 1)
    - Regional Advisory Committee
      - April 23, 1979 (Box 1)
      - April 21, 1980 (Box 1)
      - 1981 (Box 1)
    - Scientific Review Committee
      - July 21, 1978 (Box 1)
      - April 30 & May 1, 1981 (Box 1)
      - July 15 & 16 1982 (Box 1)
      - April 4, 1983 (Box 1)
      - March 29, 1984 (Box 1)
      - March 29 & 30 1984 (Box 1)
    - Subcommittee on Education and Outreach Programs 1980-1981 (Box 1)
    - Subcommittee on Health Care Delivery Research and Training
      - Agendas, Meeting Materials, etc. 1980 (Box 1)
      - Correspondence and Memos 1980-1981 (Box 1)
      - Data Management November 1980 (Box 1)
      - Minutes December 1980-February 1981 (Box 2)
  - Conception and Planning
    - Background Memos, Minutes, Proposal for MDRTC January-May 1976 (Box 2)
    - Model Demonstration Unit (MDU) Levels of Care and Write-ups December 1976 (Box 2)
    - Model Demonstration Unit (MDU) Training, Education February 1976 (Box 2)
    - Planning Committee, Minutes and Correspondence November 1980-May 1981 (Box 2)
    - Planning Subcommittee on Biomedical Research Programs January 1981 (Box 2)
    - Research Proposals 1976 (Box 2)
  - Grant Process
    - Analysis of MDRTC Grant in Light of Research Plans November 1976 (Box 2)
    - Guidelines 1976-1977 (Box 2)
    - National Institute of Arthritis, Metabolism, and Digestive Diseases (NIAMDD) Communications Regarding Initial Grant Application and April Site Visit February-June 1977 (Box 2)
    - Notice of Grant Award August 1978 (Box 2)
    - Reviews of Proposal 1977 (Box 2)
    - Site Visit Agenda [Preparation for Site Visit] March-April 1977 (Box 2)
    - Site Visit Preparation, Models of DRTC, Working Papers 1976-1977 (Box 2)
  - Renewal
    - Competing Renewal Interviews March-July 1980 (Box 2)
    - DRTC Progress Report July 1978 (Box 2)
    - Mock Site Visit October 1981 (Box 2)
    - Keatha Krueger (Diabetes Center Program Director, National Institutes of Health) Annual Report to Congress 1982, 1983, 1985, 3 folders (Box 2)
    - Memos Regarding Keatha Krueger Visits 1980-1982 (Box 2)
    - Competitive Renewal Application planning 1996 (Box 2)
  - Research
    - Clinical Centers [Regarding Possibility of Becoming NIH Clinical Trial Site for Two Separate Projects] 1978-1981 (Box 2)
    - Pilot Feasibility Grants January 1983 (Box 2)
    - Pilot Feasibility Study (Role of Cellular Cytotoxicity in Prediabetes and Diabetes) August 1983 (Box 2)
    - Pilot Feasibility Study (Sialic Acid and Diabetes Mellitus; David Aminoff) January 1982 (Box 2)
    - Research Applications Reviewed at Scientific Review Committee July 1980 (Box 2)
    - Planning on Economics Modeling Core 1996 (Box 2)
    - Visiting Consultants
      - Gerich, John March 27-28, 1980 (Box 2)
      - Knowler, William December 1980-January 1981 (Box 2)
      - Krueger, Keatha March 9-10, 1980 (Box 2)
      - Luft, Rolf March 12-13, 1981 (Box 2)
      - Miscellaneous Consultants 1979-1982 (Box 2)
      - Rehfeld, Jens May 7-8, 1981 (Box 2)
      - Santiago, Julio, October 25-26 1979 (Box 2)
      - Weir, Gordon, Itinerary, January 17-18 (Box 2)
  - Other
    - Cohn, Mickey [Administrative Core], Correspondence and Memos 1977-1980 (Box 2)
    - Criteria Retreat [Care Criteria Writing Retreat] March 20-21, 1978 (Box 2)
    - Data Management 1979-1980 (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous Memos 1978-1982 (Box 2)
    - Operations Division--MDU December 1976 (Box 2)
    - Parkview/Turner--MDU [Includes 4 Black and White Photographs of Parkview Medical] October 1977 (Box 2)
    - Research News (University of Michigan publication), issue devoted to DRTC, May 1979 (Box 2)
    - Staffing/Job Descriptions 1978-1979 (Box 2)
    - Thoburn, Norm [Correspondence To, From, and Regarding] 1980-1982 (Box 2)
    - University Hospital article, Fall 1980 (Box 2)
- Training and Demonstration Program (Diabetes Center Unit [DCU])
  The Training and Demonstration Program (Diabetes Center Unit [DCU]) series (1.4 linear feet, 1976-1985) documents the development and running of the Diabetes Center Unit, the component responsible for research in professional training and patient care. This series contains guidelines and manuals for patient care and education, both in-patient and outpatient, and minutes of the operating committee (1977-1984).
  - Aims and Programs 1978 (Box 2)
  - Care Program
    - Adult Patient Care Program Manual circa 1980, 2 folders (Box 2)
      [includes patient education materials]
    - Care Program Development Work Group 1977-1979, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Patient Care Committee (Sixth Level) August-December 1982 (Box 3)
    - Pediatric Program Manual. circa 1980 (Box 3)
  - Communication Book 1983-1985, 3 folders (Box 3)
  - Criteria Writing Meeting (Mohr, Spencer, Cjerde) July 24, 1978 (Box 3)
  - Data Definition Task Team [Development of Data Management] 1978 (Box 3)
  - Database (Margaret Chon) 1981-1982 (Box 3)
  - Diagnostic and Practical Guidelines 1976-1985 (Box 3)
  - Dietetics
    - Callaghan, Carol 1980 (Box 3)
    - Lasicheli, Andrea 1979-1982 (Box 3)
    - Mercer, Nelda [copy of research proposal by John Floyd] January 20, 1982 (Box 3)
    - Owen, George (Nutrition) 1978-1980 (Box 3)
  - Evaluation and Audit 1981-1983 (Box 3)
  - Head Nurse/Assistant Head Nurse Council (HN/AHN) 1979-1985, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Howard, Margaret (Head Nurse), Correspondence 1980-1984 (Box 3)
  - Memos Regarding Personnel, Audits, Management 1978-1982 (Box 3)
  - Medical Nursing--Dietetics, meeting minutes September 10, 1982-February 22, 1983 (Box 3)
  - Operating Committee 1977-1984, 5 folders (Box 3)
  - Outpatient Clinic 1978-1981 (Box 4)
  - Outpatient Education Planning Group June 1980, September 1981 (Box 4)
  - Outpatient Evaluation Group March 3, 1981 (Box 4)
  - Patient Education
    - Course Guides 1978-1983 (Box 4)
    - Patient Education Committee Minutes, Memos, etc. 1982-1983 (Box 4)
    - Patient Education Program, Linda Strodtman 1979 (Box 4)
  - Physical Planning 1976-1979 (Box 4)
  - Progress Reports May-October 1978 (Box 4)
  - Redman, Barbara K., Consultant 1977-1978 (Box 4)
  - Research Coordinating Committee 1978-1979 (Box 4)
  - Spencer, Martha L. [Acting Coordinator] 1978-1979 (Box 4)
  - Staff
    - Adult Staff Feedback Seminar 1980 (Box 4)
    - Proposed Nursing Staff 1977 (Box 4)
    - Staff Meetings 1980-1984 (Box 4)
- Continuing Education and Outreach Program
  The final series, Continuing Education and Outreach Program (0.5 linear feet, 1978-1998), contains records from the continuing education and outreach core facility (CEDO), which studies patients' adjustment to diabetes, and from the educational development and evaluation core facility (EDEV), which focuses on patient education.
  - Continuing Education Development and Outreach (CEDO), Correspondence and Memos 1978-1980 (Box 4)
  - Audiovisual Resources for Diabetes Education 1978 (Box 4)
  - Educational Development and Evaluation (EDEV), Data Management 1982 (Box 4)
  - MDRTC Training and Information Transfer Division (TRIT) Materials 1988 (Box 4)
  - Clinical Implementation Core (CIC) Clinic Development (Box 4)
  - Development and Education Division Planning (1997-2002) 1996-1997 (Box 4)
  - Diabetes Care Profile and Diabetes History 1998 (Box 4)
Related Material
Related record groups held by the Bentley Historical Library include the Department of Postgraduate Medicine and Health Professions Education (see the series Administrative Files), the Department of Internal Medicine (see the series Division Files), and the Linda Strodtman collection (for papers of Linda Strodtman and Stefan Fajans).